欢迎大家来到国际数学家大会（ICM）的公众讲座。
Welcome everyone to the public lecture of the International Congress of Mathematicians.
我非常荣幸向大家介绍我们的演讲者 Terence Tao（陶哲轩）。
It's a great pleasure and honor for me to introduce our speaker, Terence Tao.
陶哲轩在普林斯顿大学师从 Elias Stein（伊莱亚斯·斯坦）获得博士学位，随后加入 UCLA，
Terry received his PhD from Elias Stein at Princeton University and then moved to UCLA,
此后一直留在那里，现为该校杰出教授
where he's been ever since, where he's now the Distinguished Professor
并担任 James and Carol Collins 讲席教授。
and the James and Carol Collins Chair.
数学。
Mathematics.
如果我要列举他所有的研究成果和荣誉，
If I tried to list all of his various research accomplishments and accolades,
我们整晚都列不完，大家就没机会听他演讲了。
we'd be here all night and you'd never get to hear a word from him.
所以我只提一下，他曾在往届 ICM 上获得菲尔兹奖，
So I'll just mention that he won the Fields Medal at a previous ICM,
以及 Breakthrough Prize 等许多其他奖项。
the Breakthrough Prize, many, many other awards.
我们将在最后安排问答。
We will take questions at the end.
最后将在外面右侧门厅进行约 10 分钟的问答。
There's going to be a 10-minute Q&A outside in the foyer to the right.
现在，请大家和我一起欢迎陶哲轩教授。
And otherwise, I hope you'll join me in welcoming Professor Terry Tao.
非常感谢。很高兴能再次亲身来到 ICM 现场。
Well, thank you very much. It's such a pleasure to be here again at ICM in person.
已经过了相当长时间，我重新见到了许多老朋友，
It's been quite a while and I've reconnected a lot of old friends
我也在感受这里的积极能量。
and just absorbing the positive energy.
我的演讲主题也许是如今大家都在讨论的话题，
So my talk is about maybe the topic everyone is talking about these days,
AI 时代以及它对数学意味着什么。
the era of AI and what it means for mathematics.
我们似乎生活在一个剧变的时代，
So, you know, we seem to live in an era of great change,
而这可能是
and that's something that's not,
我们不习惯的，因为数学已经在一个多世纪里保持非常稳定。
we may not be accustomed to because mathematics has been very stable for over a century.
我们没有经历过真正重大的存在性危机之类的事情。
Things, we haven't had real big existential crises or anything.
但如今忽然之间，我们的变化似乎相当大。
But now suddenly, we seem to be changing quite a lot.
这看起来前所未有，但实际上，
And it seems unprecedented, but actually,
我认为我们正在经历的事情有历史先例。
I think there are historical precedents for what we're going through.
作为引言，我想先谈谈
So, as a prologue, I'll just talk about
一个世纪前发生的数学基础危机。
the crisis in foundations which happened a century ago.
在 20 世纪之交以前，
So before the turn of the 20th century,
我们数学家的工作方式半形式化，我们已有欧几里得，
we mathematicians operated semi-formally, you know, we had Euclid,
我们也知道证明，但我们没有完全公理化我们的
we knew about proof, but we didn't fully axiomatize our
逻辑基础以及
foundations of logic and
集合、分析，
and sets and analysis and, you know,
我们在很大程度上使用某种非形式化的朴素基础。
we largely used kind of informal naive foundations.
因此，像集合究竟是什么、数是什么、函数是什么，
So questions like what actually is a set or what is a number, what is a function,
极限是什么？
what is a limit?
我们有一些规则，但没有真正完整写下数学的公理。
We had some rules, but we didn't really write down fully the axioms of mathematics.
这种情况一直持续到 20 世纪初，那时一些哲学家突然
And that worked until the early 20th century, when suddenly these philosophers,
当时只有他们在思考这些问题，
who were the only ones who were thinking about these questions,
指出以朴素方式处理其实存在一些严重问题。
pointed out that there were actually some serious problems with doing things naively.
例如伯特兰·罗素，
So Bertrand Russell, for example,
是一位哲学家，他指出朴素集合论是不一致的。
was a philosopher who pointed out that naive set theory was inconsistent.
你可以构造一个既包含自身又不包含自身的集合。
You could construct a set that both contained itself and didn't contain itself.
当然，哥德尔提出了不完备性定理，
And of course, Gödel had incompleteness theorems
即没有任何公理系统能完全
that there's no system of axioms that could ever completely
证明或否证你在算术等领域中能提出的所有问题。
prove or disprove all the questions you could ask in, say, arithmetic.
于是我们被迫真正认真思考我们的数学基础，
And so we were forced to actually really think about our foundations
以及什么是证明，我们这门职业的规则是什么。
and what is a proof, what are the rules of our profession?
那段经历是创伤性的。
And that was traumatic.
它被称为数学基础危机。
It is called the crisis in foundations.
那时充满动荡，有大量辩论和争论。
And it was turbulent. It was a lot of debate and argument.
但最终我们从中得到了非常有价值的东西。
But we came out of it at the end with something very valuable.
我们有了做数学的标准框架。
We had a standard framework for doing mathematics.
我们有一套正统规则，一阶逻辑，
We have an orthodox set of rules, first-order logic,
以及带选择公理的 Zermelo-Fraenkel 集合论，
Zermelo-Fraenkel choice set theory,
它已标准化，我们也有共识认为它
and it's standardized and we have a consensus that it's
足以胜任几乎所有数学。
it's good enough to do almost all the mathematics.
这并非最终答案。人们仍在研究其他基础，
Now it's not the final word. People still study other foundations,
并将其与 ZFC 进行比较。
compare them to ZFC.
例如，Lean
for example, the Lean
这种形式化证明助手语言并不基于 ZFC。
formal proof assistant language is not based on ZFC.
例如，它基于依赖类型理论。
It's based on dependent type theory, for instance.
但这没关系。我们也在研究其他基础，
Um, but that's fine. Uh, we are, we are studying other foundations,
但不是从危机的立场出发。
but not from a position of crisis.
对，我们研究它就像研究任何其他科学或数学对象一样。
Right, we're studying it just like any other scientific or mathematical object to study.
而且几个世纪以来，我们已经对这些基础进行了严格的检验。
And we've tested these foundations, you know, strenuously over the centuries.
而且我们相信，我们……
And we trust, you know, that we, you know, I mean,
理论上仍可能存在严重问题，
there's still theoretically the possibility that there is a serious problem in,
在这些基础中。
in these foundations.
但它们似乎有效，并且已经有效运作了一个世纪。
But they seem to work and they've worked for a century.
所以我认为，在那场危机一个世纪之后，
So I will argue that one century after that crisis,
我们正进入一个同样动荡的时期。
we are now entering a similarly turbulent period.
顺便说一下，对于喜欢在文本中发现破折号的人，
And just for people who like spotting em dashes in text,
这是一个人类生成的破折号，只是为了强调这一点。
this was a human-generated em dash, just to emphasize that.
但这不是我们数学论证中的危机，
But it's not a crisis in our mathematical arguments
而是我们数学价值观和实践中的危机。
but it's a crisis in our mathematical values and practices that we have.
我们过去某种程度上一直在关于“数学是什么”的朴素基础上运作。
We had kind of been operating on naive foundations of what mathematics is.
而这些基础突然得出了相当奇怪的结论。
And suddenly they are reaching rather strange conclusions.
我们确实需要重新审视并恰当地重建这些基础。
And we do need to reexamine and rebuild these foundations properly.
但同样，一旦我们这样做，这将是非常有价值的经历。
But again, it will be a very worthwhile experience once we do that.
我们的学科会健康得多、有韧性得多，
Our subject will be much healthier, much more resilient,
而且我们将能够恰当地整合所有这些新技术。
and we will be able to incorporate all these new technologies properly.
那么我这次演讲的主题是什么？
All right, so what is the topic of my talk?
我可以把它表述为，可以说是一个大问题，如果你愿意的话，
So I can phrase it as sort of, you know, the big question, if you wish,
驱动这一切的大问题，就是我所称的“共同体回应问题”。
that motivates everything is what I call the community response question.
好吗？
Okay?
那么，数学共同体应如何回应现代 AI 的到来
So how should the mathematical community respond to the advent of modern AI
以及随之而来的各种相关事物？
technologies and all the related things that come with it.
而且，事实上它们要么已经拥有，要么声称拥有
And, you know, the fact that they either have or they claim to have capabilities to
执行数学任务的能力。
perform mathematical tasks.
这是个大问题，而且是整个共同体的问题。
So this is a big question and it's a question for the entire community.
没有人，即便是 IMU（国际数学联盟），
You know, no one, not even the IMU,
也不能直接制定规则让我们都照做。
can just lay down some rules and we can all follow them.
我们必须切实讨论这个问题，就像我们当年不得不讨论
We have to actually debate this question just like how we had to debate the
数理逻辑的基础一样。
foundations of mathematical logic.
但我确实有一些意见，算是开始这场讨论。
But I do have some comments to sort of start discussion.
不过，这不是一个数学问题。
Now, this is not a math question.
这不是一个会有一个证明
This is not, this is not a conjecture where there's going to be a proof
和唯一答案的猜想。
and a single answer.
这是一个元数学问题，同时也是一个政治问题、
This is a meta-mathematical question and, you know, also a political question,
伦理问题、文化问题、经济问题等等。
ethical question, cultural, economic, whatever.
所以它不是数学问题。
So it's not a math question.
然而，我认为非常仔细地、
However, I think the mindset of thinking very carefully
以数学方式思考问题的心态非常有用。
and mathematically about problems is very useful.
所以我将以一种准数学的方式来处理这个问题。
So I'm going to tackle this question pseudo-mathematically.
我将使用数学语言来分析这个问题，
I'm going to use the language of mathematics to try to analyze this question,
尽管它不是一个数学问题。
even though it is not a mathematical question.
希望因为在座各位很多都是数学家，
And hopefully, because so many of you in the audience are mathematicians,
这能帮助澄清我想表达的观点。
this will help clarify the points I'm trying to make.
所以我们关心的是这个共同体回应问题。
Okay, so we're interested in this community response question.
面对 AI，我们该做什么？
What should we do in response to AI?
所以有一个子问题，它在过去三年里主导了讨论，
And so there's a sub question which has dominated debate over the last three
但它是一个略有不同的问题。
years, but it's a slightly different question.
所以我称之为“AI 能力猜想”。
Um, and so this I will call the AI capability conjecture.
我说了我会用数学语言，
So I said I'm using the language of mathematics,
所以我要把它称为一个猜想。
so I'm going to call this a conjecture.
而且严格来说，它不是一个单一的猜想。
Um, and actually technically it's not a single conjecture.
而是一族猜想。
It's a family of conjectures.
我在这里把这个猜想作为一个模板来陈述，
Um, so this conjecture I'm stating here as a template,
其中有一些占位符，或者如果你想保持数学语言，可以称为变量。
there's some placeholders or variables if you want to keep the mathematical language.
所以它……是因为变量太多，
Um, and so, uh, it, it, it's, it's so, because there's so many variables,
这个猜想几乎可以表示任何意思，但我还是把它说出来。
This conjecture could mean almost anything, but I will say it anyway.
这个猜想声称，在不久的将来某个时候，一些 AI 工具将，
So the conjecture states that at some point in the near future, some AI tools will,
在一些成本和一定程度的人类监督下，
with some expense and some level of human supervision,
能够在某些数学领域完成一些研究级数学任务，
be able to accomplish some research level mathematical tasks in some fields of
并以一些非平凡的成功率和一定程度的正确性完成。
mathematics with some nontrivial success rate and some level of correctness.
以及质量。现在，
And quality. Now,
我在这里塞了这么多“some”，以至于它几乎可以表示任何意思。
I've put so many "some"s in here that this could be almost anything.
因此，近年来很多争论在某种程度上已经变成了：究竟……
And so a lot of the debate has sort of devolved in recent years as to exactly
你应当在这些不同的空位里给“some”填上哪个值。
which value of "some" should you put in different slots here.
而这不是我今天演讲的重点。
And that's not the point of my talk today.
我认为这实际上分散了人们对一些更根本问题的注意力。
I think that's actually distracting from some more fundamental issues.
所以请把它看作一族猜想。
So just think of this as a family of conjectures.
当然，你可以把“some”设成少数几个，从而使它成为一个非常弱的猜想，
Of course, you could make this a very weak conjecture by making "some" just a few,
或者，你也可以使它非常强。
or, you know, or you can make it very strong.
你可以在自己脑海里做一个 Mad Lib 式的填空，
You can just sort of insert in your own personal mental Mad Lib, you know what,
你在这里可以填什么。
what you can put here.
所以让我只是相当粗略地谈谈强、弱
So let me just sort of vaguely talk about strong and weak
以及这个猜想的中间形式。
and intermediate forms of this conjecture.
好。
All right.
所以很明显，知道这个猜想或这一族猜想的答案
So it's kind of clear that knowing the answer to this conjecture or family of
很重要，因为，例如，
conjectures is important because, you know, for example,
如果这个猜想甚至连弱版本都不成立，
if even weak versions of this conjecture happen to be false like that.
这些工具对于研究级任务大体上无用，
You know, that these tools were largely useless for research level tasks,
那就没什么可争论的了，这些只是新奇玩意儿，
then there's no debate, you know, I mean, these are novelties, you know,
少数人可能会玩一玩它们。
some small minority of people could play with them.
但是，数学基本上可以照常运转。
But, you know, math could basically continue business as usual.
另一方面，如果这个猜想的最强版本为真，
Um, on the other hand, if the strongest versions of this conjecture are true
而且数学家今天所做的每一项任务，
and every single task that mathematicians do today,
AI 都能做得更好、更快，以及等等。
AIs can do better and faster and, whatever.
那么，是的，那显然我们就不能继续照常运转，
Then, yeah, then clearly we cannot continue business as usual,
尤其是如果我们专注于 AI 最擅长的事情。
particularly if we focus on the things that the AIs do best.
例如，解决未解决问题似乎就是它们的强项之一，
For example, solving unsolved problems seems to be one of their strengths and
而这似乎也是我们经常做的事情之一。
that seems to be one of the things that we do a lot.
我们甚至名义上还会为这些事情颁发奖章。
We even give out medals for these things, ostensibly.
那么我们实际上必须思考，
Um, so then we have to actually, uh, think about, uh,
我们的文化和实践；如果中间某种情况为真，那么我们……
our culture and practices, and if something in the middle is true, then we,
我们就必须更加仔细地思考。
we have to think, uh, even more carefully.
如我所说，如果你看看媒体上的所有争论，
Okay, so as I said, if you look at all the debates in the media
可能还有喝咖啡时，在公共休息室里，以及
and probably over coffee, uh, you know, in common rooms and, and,
以及在互联网上。
and on the internet.
因为共同体对这个问题如何回应，在很大程度上取决于
Um, you know, because the answer to the community response question depends
对 AI 能力猜想的回答。
so much on the answer to the AI capability conjecture.
因此，争论的很大一部分一直围绕能力展开。
So much of the debate has been about capability.
而且，是的，我本人也确实参与过这种讨论。
Um, and, um, yeah, so, and I have certainly, um, participated in this.
如果你看看，我过去三年里经常谈论 AI。
If you look at, I've spoken about AI a lot in the last three years.
我经常谈论能力，因为它很重要，
And I talk a lot about the capability because it is important
而且三年前确实有一段时间，
and there was certainly a time three years ago
当时能力还很差，但它正朝着好得多的方向发展。
where the capability was very poor, but it was trending to be a lot better.
我们确实需要澄清“我们当时所处的位置”和……
And we really had to clarify the distinction between where we were and
“这项技术正在走向何方”之间的区别。
where the technology was going.
但这次演讲不是关于那个猜想。
But this talk is not about that conjecture.
哦，等一下。我会讲到那一点的。
Um, oh, hang on. I will get to that.
但是，如果你关注互联网，我相信你已经听说过很多，
But, um, um, now if you follow the internet, I'm sure, uh, you have heard many,
很多断言，以及各种反驳，
many claims and, um, and counterclaims and,
以及关于这个猜想在不同层面上是真是假的争论。
and arguments about whether this conjecture is true or false in various levels.
所以我们现在有很多数据点。
Um, and so we have a lot of data points now.
某个具体问题被解决了，但接着，这个……
This, you know, specific problem has been solved and then, but then, uh, this,
这个 AI 甚至不能乘两位数，或者等等。
this AI can't even, you know, multiply two-digit numbers or, or whatever.
我们拥有的大部分数据并不是在适当的科学条件下收集的。
Most of the data we have is not gathered under proper scientific conditions.
我们有点像是选择性地披露了一些看起来令人印象深刻的结果，
We have sort of selectively disclosed results which look impressive,
但我们并不确切知道输入是什么。
but we don't know exactly what the inputs were.
我们不知道真正的失败率是多少。
We don't know the proper failure rate.
而许多披露这些结果的公司都有自己的动机，
And many of the companies that are disclosing these have their own incentives to,
或许去尽可能以有利的方式呈现结果
to maybe, uh, uh, present the results in as favorable a light as possible
并且不披露重要信息，比如实际要花费多少成本
and not reveal important information like, say, how much it cost
才能得到这些结果。
to actually produce these results.
所以这是一个非常混乱的局面。
Um, so it is, it is a very confusing mess.
目前，这整个，所有这些数据点，比如支持
Uh, right now, um, this, this whole, uh, all the data points like, for
以及反对这个猜想的。
against this conjecture.
另一点是，
Um, and also another point is, is that, um,
人们有时会混淆这个猜想是真是假
people sometimes conflate whether this conjecture is true or false
以及我们希望它是真是假。
as to whether we want it to be true or false.
我认为那也未必一致。
And I think that may not necessarily align either.
所以我不会讨论这个猜想。
So I won't be talking about this conjecture.
我要指出的一件事是，我们确实有，
The one thing I will point you to is that we do have,
我们开始有了一些更系统、更科学的评估
we are starting to have some more systematic and scientific assessments
对 AI 能力的评估。
of AI capability.
所以我认为最有前景的是第一个 Proof Challenge（证明挑战），
So I think the most promising is the first Proof Challenge,
你们很多人听说过。
which many of you have heard about.
这是一项由数学家发起的草根项目，
So this is a grassroots effort run by mathematicians
它是对当今 AI 模型状况的一次独立评估。
and it's an independent assessment of the state of AI models today.
它不由任何主要 AI 公司赞助。
It is not sponsored by any major AI company.
它的做法是找来一批数学家，
What it does is that it creates a batch of mathematicians,
捐赠一批10个尚未发表的研究级问题。
donate a batch of 10 research level problems that have not been published.
这些问题的解答也尚未发表，
The solutions have not been published,
所有问题本身，
all the problems themselves
然后用这些问题去测试完全自主的 AI 模型。
and they test them against completely autonomous AI models.
例如，在五月，提交了四个测试框架。
Um, and so for example, back in May, uh, there were, uh, four harnesses submitted.
我参与的一个团队制作了其中之一。
Uh, I was involved in a team that made one of them.
他们对它们进行测试，尝试测试这10个问题。
Um, and they tested them to try to test these 10 problems.
在这四个测试框架中，他们不只是问这些，
And between those four harnesses, um, they didn't just ask whether the, the, uh,
这些问题是否被解决，而是问它们是否被写成文字
these problems were solved, but whether they were written up
并且以能达到发表质量的方式解释清楚。
and explained in a way that would be publication quality.
比如，这是否真的合理，可以发表在一篇论文、一本期刊中，
Like, would it actually be reasonable, um, to publish in a paper, in a journal,
也许只需要一些轻微的，修改之类的。
maybe with some slight, um, corrections or something.
而且，我认为，最佳单项记录，我想，
Um, and, uh, uh, I think the, uh, the best individual record, I think, uh,
是某个测试框架达到了十分之五。
was like five out of 10 for one harness.
但整体上，它们能够以发表质量解决十分之七，
But collectively they were able to solve seven out of 10 at publication
但代价不低。
quality, but at a non-trivial cost.
每个测试框架在每个问题上都必须花费，
Each harness had to spend on each problem,
成本从10到1000美元不等。
the cost ranged anywhere from 10 to 1,000 US dollars.
所以这大致是五月时的情况。现在他们会继续测试。
So that's roughly where we were at in May. Now they're going to keep testing.
这些批次，也许这些统计数据会改变，
These batches and maybe these stats will change,
但我要说，这是我们目前拥有的最科学的数据点，对吗？
but I would say this is the most scientific data point we have right now, okay?
所以我不再讨论这个猜想了。
So I'm not going to talk about this conjecture anymore.
我要讨论这个猜想的补充问题。
I'm going to talk about the complement of this conjecture.
如果我们假设这个猜想在某种意义上成立，
What if we suppose this conjecture is true in a certain, in a certain sense?
那么，数学共同体应该如何回应？
What then do we do about community response?
所以如各位所知，像数学家通常做的那样，我会提出一个假设，对吗？
So I will make a, as you know, as mathematicians do, we'll make a hypothesis, okay?
我会提出一个工作假设：我之前说的所有“某些”
I'll make a working hypothesis where all the 'some's that I said
都将被“合理”取代。
before will now be replaced by 'reasonable'.
所以一个强度合理的猜想成立。
Okay, so a reasonably strong conjecture is true.
在不远的将来，AI 将能够完成相当一部分
You know, relatively soon AI will be able to perform a reasonable fraction of
数学任务，并在成功程度、质量和成本方面达到合理水平。
mathematical tasks with reasonable levels of success, quality, and cost.
我不会定义“合理”是什么意思。那么，
And I will not define what reasonable means. Okay, so,
但你可以在脑海中大致形成某个概念。
but you can sort of put in your mind some idea.
这是一个假设，在数学中我们有时会做出假设。
Okay, so this is an assumption, okay, in math, we sometimes make an assumption.
我们不知道它是真还是假，
We don't know whether it's true or false,
但我们感兴趣的是探索其推论。
but we are interested in exploring its consequences.
我将做一个条件分析。
I'm going to do a conditional analysis.
你可以争论这个猜想、这个假设是真还是假。
You can argue whether this conjecture, this hypothesis is true or false.
这不是本次演讲的重点。
That is not the point of this talk.
我只是有条件地假设它成立。
I'm just going to assume it conditionally.
所以一旦你基于这个假设，
So once you condition on the hypothesis
也就是 AI 确实能解决相当一部分
that AI will actually solve a, a reasonable fraction of, uh,
我们今天作为数学家所做的工作。
of things that we currently do today as mathematicians.
变得清楚的是，为了继续前进，
Uh, what becomes clear is, is that in order to proceed.
并回答这个回应问题。我们现在必须思考我们的目标和价值。
And answer the response question. We now have to think about our goals and our values.
所以我认为这确实是我们今天需要讨论的重要问题。
And so really, this is, I think, the important question we need to discuss today.
我指的不只是字面意义上的今天，而是当前这个时代。
I mean, not just literally today, but, but in this current era.
这就是我所说的目标和价值问题。
So this is what I call the goals and values question.
那么，我们共同体的精确目标、目的和价值
So what are the precise goals, objectives and values of our community
以及一般数学研究的目标、目的和价值究竟是什么？
and of mathematical research in general?
我们有明确的目标，我们
Now, we have explicit goals, you know, we,
当我们发布新闻稿、写论文摘要，或
when we make press releases or when we write abstracts for our papers or
申请研究经费时，我们会列出，
when we apply for funding grants, we'd list, you know,
这是这个项目的目标之类。
this is the objective of this project or whatever.
那些是明确目标。
Those are explicit goals.
但我们发现，实际上还有很多隐性目标
But what we're finding is that actually there's also a lot of implicit goals
我们讨论得不够，而现在讨论这些突然变得非常重要。
that we don't talk about enough, and it's suddenly very important that we do so.
让我解释为什么。
So let me explain why.
过去，我们主要专注于技术目标，
So in the past, you know, we, we focused mostly on technical goals,
比如，我想改进这个常数，我想
you know, like, um, I want to improve this constant, you know, I, I want to, to,
证明这个定理。
to prove this theorem.
我想找到一个满足 X、Y 和 Z 的定义。可以吧？
I want to find a definition that does X, Y and Z. Okay?
而关于价值和目标，以及
Um, and questions about values and goals and, you know, what is,
数学的目的是什么的问题，
what is the purpose of mathematics?
我们曾认为这是人文学科的问题。
We thought that this was a question for the humanities.
也许数学哲学家会处理这个问题，
You know, maybe philosophers of mathematics would tackle this question or
或者科学社会学家、数学教育者等等，但
sociologists of science or, um, or math educators or, or, or, you know, but, um,
所以我们可能过于、过多地
you know, so, uh, we, we have focused maybe overly, too much, uh,
专注于技术层面。
on the technical aspects.
因为那是我们最擅长的。
Uh, because that was what we were best at.
而且在某些方面，技术层面更容易处理，
Um, and in some ways it's sort of easier to, to work with, uh,
尽管数学本身往往也相当困难。
despite math itself being, uh, quite, quite difficult sometimes.
但我要论证的是，如果接受这个工作假设，
But I'm going to argue that, you know, if you assume the working hypothesis,
我们就不再拥有不披露、
we will not have the luxury anymore of not disclosing,
不真正披露我们目标的奢侈了。
not really disclosing our goals.
而且我认为这是健康的。
And I think it's healthy.
所以不管这个假设是真、假还是部分为真
So, you know, regardless of whether this hypothesis is true or false or partly true
或其他，我认为这实际上已经早该
or whatever, I think it is actually overdue
讨论我们为什么做数学
that we do need to talk about why we do mathematics
以及我们学科真正的目的是什么。而且我们会，会，会
and what is the real purpose of our subject. Um, and we will, we will, we will be
因此变得更强大。
Stronger, uh, for doing so.
那么我们为什么做研究？为什么我们尝试解决问题，
So why do we do research? Why do we try to solve problems and, and, and, uh,
探索数学概念？
and explore mathematical concepts?
实际上有很多原因。
And there's actually a lot of reasons. Um,
我认为没有人列过完整清单。
and I don't think anyone has compiled a complete list.
这里只是其中一些。当然，我们解决开放未解问题。
Uh, here are just some, you know, so of course we solve open unsolved problems.
这很重要。
That is important.
既包括纯问题，也就是
Um, both pure problems you know problems that
在数学之外没有任何直接应用的问题，
that don't have any direct application outside of mathematics,
也包括许多重要的应用问题。
but also many important applied problems.
这是数学非常重要的动机。
It's a very important motivation for mathematics.
我们喜欢开发新工具、新理论、新技术。
We like to develop new tools, new theories, new techniques.
我们喜欢更好地理解数学。我们喜欢理解周围的世界。
We like to understand mathematics better. We like to understand the world around us.
世界充满模式，正如我们在 Hannah Fry 的演讲中所见。
You know, the world is full of patterns as, as we saw in, in Hannah Fry's lecture.
我们想理解这个世界。
Um, you know, and we, we want to understand, um, the world.
但数学也是一门社会性很强的学科。
Um, but we also, you know, math is also a very social subject.
数学，
Um, you know, um, math, you know,
我们对数学感到兴奋，很大一部分是因为我们可以把它传达给，
we are excited about math in large part because we can communicate to,
给共同体的其他成员，我们也想建设这个共同体，而且我们想，
to the rest of our community and we want to build that community and, uh, we want to,
我们想培养下一代。我们想延续这件事。
we want to train the next generation. We want to sustain this.
这个共同体。
Community.
所以我们投入了大量精力来，
So, you know, we, we invest a lot of effort in,
提升和教育下一代数学家，他们将做出
in lifting up and educating the next generation of mathematicians who will do things
我们无法梦想的事情。
that, that we can't dream of.
我们拥有这个庞大的数学知识库，
And we have this huge database of mathematical knowledge
它已经积累了数千年。
that's been building for thousands of years.
我们拥有几乎是地球上最古老、连续不断、
We have almost the the oldest continuous,
持续发展的累积知识库。
continually developing cumulative knowledge base on the planet.
而且，我们为此做出贡献。这很了不起。
And, and, you know, we contribute to that. That's amazing.
而这种美学价值，我们常常低估，但它也很重要。
And this aesthetic value, which we often downplay, but it is also important.
数学是美的。
You know, mathematics is beautiful.
而且，你可以创造出某种东西，
And, you know, you can create something that,
人们会欣赏几个世纪，而这也是一种价值。
that people will admire for centuries and that, that also is, is, is a value.
而且，你可以，这是你们的作业。
And you can, you know, it's your homework.
你可以给这个列表再加上两条。
You can add two more bullet points to this list.
所以我们有所有这些目标，但我们往往一次只说出其中一两个。
So we have all these goals and we tend to only state one or two of them at a time.
直到最近，这大致还好，因为它们都是对齐的。
And until recently, that was kind of fine because they were all aligned.
所以我们有所有这些目标，它们略有不同，但数学曾经很难，
So we had all these goals and they're slightly different goals, but math was hard,
而我们距离实现其中许多目标还非常遥远。
and we're very far from attaining many of these goals.
解决问题很困难。证明事情也很困难。
You know, solving problems is difficult. Proving things is difficult.
每件事都曾经很困难。
Everything was difficult.
所以只要你离所有这些目标还很远，
And so as long as you're far away from all these goals,
只要它们彼此大致相关。
as long as they're kind of roughly correlated with each other.
你就可以朝一个目标前进，而且你，
You can move towards one goal and you'd,
你也会同时朝着其他目标前进。
you'd also be moving towards other goals as well.
所以因为这种正相关，
So you, we, we, so because of this positive correlation,
你可以只明确说出一个目标，它就可以作为所有其他目标的代理。
you can just state one goal explicitly and, and it can be a proxy for all the others.
你不必说明，如果你能只说，我，
You don't need to state, you know, if you can just say, I'm,
我要做目标一，我也暗中想做目标二，但我知道
I'm gonna do Goal 1, I also secretly want to do Goal 2, but I know
通过推动目标一，我也在更接近目标二。
that by pushing towards Goal 1, I am getting closer to Goal 2 as well.
所以我们当时并不真的需要说出所有目标。
So we didn't really need to state all our goals.
那么这一直有效，直到你开始大量优化，并且变得非常擅长，比如说，目标一。
Okay, so this works until you start optimizing a lot and you become very good at, say, Goal 1.
到某个时候，你变得如此擅长目标一，
And at some point, you become so good at Goal 1
以至于朝着目标一的任何进一步进展，实际上会让你远离目标二、三、四和五。
that any further progress towards Goal 1 actually moves you away from Goal 2, 3, 4 and 5.
这是一个非常，众所周知的，
Um, and this is a very, um, well known, uh,
经济学中的现象，称为古德哈特定律，即
phenomenon in economics known as Goodhart's law that
当一个衡量指标变成目标时，
when a measure becomes a target,
如果你对任何特定指标优化过度，它就不再是一个好的衡量指标。
it ceases to be a good measure if you optimize too much for any specific metric.
可以说，它是以其他目标为代价的，
Uh, you can say it's, it comes at the expense of other goals
而这些目标其实也是你想优化的。
that you actually wanted to optimize as well. Um, and, um.
是的，对人类来说，当人类做这件事时，
Yeah, for humans, when humans are doing this,
问题并不那么大，因为人类并不那么擅长优化。
it's not that much of a problem because humans are not that amazing at optimization.
但 AI 很擅长，AI 公司也很擅长。
But AIs are and also AI companies are.
而这是，这实际上是一个危险的组合。
And that is, and that is actually a dangerous combination.
是的，AI，AI 可以优化，不受实际现实的约束。
Yeah, the AIs, AIs can optimize, uh, untethered by, by actual reality.
所以它们特别容易受到古德哈特定律的影响。
Um, and so, uh, they are particularly vulnerable to Goodhart's law.
所以我们现在正进入一个时期，所有目标
And so we are now entering a period where all the goals
我们拥有的目标现在指向相反的、相互竞争的方向。
that we have are now pointing in opposite, in, in, in competing directions.
我认为，AI 尤其可能让我们更接近其中一个
Um, and I think, um, you know, AI in particular may get us closer to one of these
目标，但代价是牺牲其他目标。
goals, but at the expense of others.
所以我们不能再一次只专注于一个目标。
And so we can no longer afford to only focus on one goal at a time.
而对于我们确实专注的目标，
And the goals that we do focus on,
我们必须非常清楚这些目标的评判标准是什么。
we have to be really clear about what our rubric is for these goals.
所以这就是我们现在所处的局面，对吗？
So that's the situation that we are now finding ourselves in, okay?
现在我没有足够的时间讨论所有这些目标，
Now I do not have enough time to talk about all of these goals,
所以我将只专注于其中一个目标，但它是，
so I will focus on on just one of the goals, but it's,
它是最近吸引了最多关注的那一个。
it's the one that has attracted the most attention in, in, in, in recent.
近年来，也就是问题求解。
In, in, in, in recent years, which is problem solving.
所以如果你，就……而言，
Um, so, you know, if, if you, insofar as, as, uh,
当外部世界看待数学时，我觉得他们，
the outside world looks at mathematics, um, I think they have,
他们其实完全不知道我们在做什么，但看起来像是这样。
they don't really have any, any idea what we do, but it seems like.
但是看起来我们真正执着的事情之一就是
But, um, um, one of the things that it looks like we are really obsessed with is
解决开放问题。
solving open problems.
所以我将讨论我们职业的这个方面，也就是问题求解，它是，
So, um, I will discuss this, this aspect of our profession, problem solving, it is,
但不，正如我试图强调的，这并不是，
but no, as I'm trying, as I try to emphasize, this is not,
这只是我们的目标之一。
this is just one of our goals.
但我会对它进行拆解，并尝试仅就这个目标本身谈几点看法。
But I will deconstruct it and try to make some points about this goal alone.
是的。我们并不，
Yeah. I mean, we don't, you know,
我们并不是都只想尽可能多地解决问题。
we're not all just trying to solve as many problems as possible.
所以是的，许多数学家更感兴趣于构建优美的理论，或者
So yeah, many mathematicians are more interested in building beautiful theories or
或者教育下一代等等。
or educating the next generation, whatever.
这些都是非常重要的目标，但我会聚焦于，
These are all very important goals, but I will focus on the, um, uh,
问题求解这个目标，因为这是
the goal of problem solving, because this is the one
目前受到最大影响的那一个，
which is currently being impacted the most by,
也就是受到 AI 的影响，如果我们接受这个工作假说的话。
by AI if we assume this working hypothesis.
好。
Okay.
那么，这里的目标是什么？好吧。
So what is, uh, the goal here? All right.
正如我所说，从外部看，对局外人来说，
So as I said, externally, it looks like, you know, to an outsider,
这好像就是数学的目标：尽可能多地解决未解决的问题。
this is the goal of mathematics, just solve as many unsolved problems as possible.
有点像，当我，当我还是学生的时候，
Um, kind of like as if, you know, um, you know, when I was, um, when I was a student,
当我还是高中生的时候，
um, when I was a high school student,
我完全不知道一个人可以成为职业数学家。
I had no idea you could be a professional mathematician.
而我，当我得知存在这样一种工作时，
And my, when I learned that there was such a job,
我曾想象有某个由资深数学家组成的委员会
I imagined that there was some committee of senior mathematicians
会以某种方式给人们分配问题，
that would somehow assign people problems,
而我们都会把分配给自己的问题当作家庭作业来做。
and we would just all work on our assigned problems as our homework assignments.
而且，而且在某种程度上，这就是这个体系的运作方式。
And, and that was somehow the way this, the, the system worked.
而这完全不是这个体系的运作方式，
And it is totally not the way the system works,
但这有时确实是外界对它的印象。
but that is kind of what the impression of it is from the outside sometimes.
明白吗？
Okay?
所以你可以这样想，好，再次用那种伪数学语言来说，
So you can think of it as, okay, again, in the pseudo mathematical language,
我正在试图优化这个流网络。
I'm trying to optimize this flow network.
我有问题的源点和解答的汇点，
I've got the source of problems and the sink of solutions,
而这就是证明生成的流
and this is flow of proof generation
而我们正试图最大化从开放问题到解答的流。
and we're trying to maximize the flow from open problems to solutions.
好？那么，如果你试图优化这个目标，甚至早在 AI 出现之前，
Okay? So if you try to optimize this goal, so even before AI,
我们就意识到其中存在一个缺陷。
we realized there was a flaw.
如果我们说，我要，
If we say, uh, I'm, I'm gonna, um,
我们的目标是尽可能多地收集人类假说的证明。
our goal is to collect as many proofs of human hypothesis as possible.
我们很快发现这不是一个好目标，
Uh, we, we figured out very quickly this was not a good goal, um,
因为你会收到大量针对你目标的解答，
because you'd receive lots and lots of solutions to, to your goals,
而这些解答并不正确。
which are not correct.
那么，行。
Um, okay, so, fine.
所以但我们有一个明显的修正办法，
Okay, so, uh, but we have an obvious way to fix that is
那就是我们首先生成这些证明，然后检查它们是否正确。
that we first generate these proofs and then we check them to be correct.
所以现在我们的流程有两个步骤。你取开放问题，生成证明，
So now our flow has got two steps. You take open problems, you generate proofs,
你创造出未经验证的解答。
you create unverified solutions.
但接着会有一个独立的证明验证过程。
But then there's a separate proof verification process.
它会产生经过验证的解答，对吗？
It creates verified solutions, okay?
而 AI 对于某些问题，已经在这个流程的第一步上变得非常擅长，
And AI has become very good at the first step of this flow for some problems,
并非对所有问题，但对某些问题，它已经变得合理、相当不错，而且
not for all problems, but for some problems, it's become reasonable, pretty good and,
并且在第二个目标上也做得相当好。
and decently good at the second goal as well.
事实上，就第二种情况而言，这并不主要是因为 AI，尽管 AI 有所帮助，
In fact, well, in the second case, it's not so much because of AI, although AI helps,
而是因为证明助手语言中的互补发展，
but because of the complementary development in proof assistant languages,
这本身就是一个完整的话题。
which are a whole topic in itself.
但还会有其他讲座讨论这一点。
But there will be other talks about that.
这是近年来的另一项重要发展，
That's another important development in recent years,
证明助手语言的巨大进步。
the massive improvement in proof assistant languages.
所以我们明显看到证明生成
So, so we visibly see the proof generation
数学中的证明验证在某些领域已经加速
and proof verification in mathematics has accelerated in certain fields
对某些类型的问题也是如此，虽然并非均匀推进，但确实加速了。
and for certain types of problems, not uniformly, but it has accelerated.
如果我们相信，如果我们以这个工作假设为前提，
And if we believe, if we condition on this working hypothesis,
它还会继续加速。
it will continue to accelerate even more.
但接着这会带来一个新问题。
But then this leads to a new problem.
假设现在我们让这些 AI 来生成证明，
You know, suppose we now have these AIs generating these proofs,
甚至有些证明是用像 Lean 这样的形式语言写成的，
and maybe we even have proofs that are in some formal language like Lean,
而且它们已经通过验证。
and they're verified.
我们有这些十万行的证明，我们已经验证它们是正确的，
And we have these 100,000-line proofs that we've verified to be correct,
但没有人理解它们。
but no one understands them.
即使是输入提示、使用这些工具来生成证明的人，
Even the humans who entered in the prompts and used these tools to generate the proofs.
可能他们自己也不理解这些证明。
Maybe they don't understand them either.
这在某些领域已经发生了。所以你——
Um, and this is already happening in some areas. So you,
可能你听说过 Iris problems。
maybe you've heard about the Iris problems.
这是一个大约 12 个问题的列表，有些已解决，有些尚未解决，
Um, it's a list of about 12, uh, problems, some solved, some unsolved, um,
而证明在最近六个月里第一次，
and proofs for the first time in, since in the last, uh, six months, um, uh,
我们开始出现积压。
we're starting to get a backlog.
证明不断被生成，有些甚至已经在 Lean 中形式化，
You know, proofs are being generated and some are even formalized in Lean,
但还没有人类真正通读过它们，而且我们没有——
and no human has actually gone through them and we don't,
没有人类能够担保说“这是一个好证明”。
there's no human who can vouch this is, this is a good proof.
而且在很多情况下，甚至提交证明的人也会说：
And, you know, there's many cases where even the people submitting the proof say,
“这里有一个证明，但我——我没有资格去评估它。”
here's a proof, but I don't, I'm not qualified to, to evaluate it.
“我不知道它是否正确。”然后另一个人说：
I don't know whether it's correct or not. And then someone else says,
“我已经在 Lean 里检查过了。”
I've checked it in Lean.
“我还是不能——我也不能为它作证。”
I still can't, I can't vouch for it either.
这种情况还没有真正发生。
And it hasn't quite happened yet.
但我们非常接近这样一种情形：一个重大结果被证明，
But we are very, very close to a scenario in which a major result gets proved
并且通过验证，却没有人能理解它、解释它。
and verified and no human can understand, can explain it.
那将是一个非常不受欢迎的发展。
So that would be a very unwelcome development.
这意味着，如果你愿意这么说的话，这个过程至少还有一个阶段。
So what that means is that there is at least one more stage to the process, if you want to.
所以我们的目标必须更新。仅仅生成证明是不够的，
So our goal must get updated. It is not enough to generate proofs
仅仅验证证明也是不够的。
and it's not enough to verify the proofs.
证明需要被解释得足够清楚，以便它们能够被传达
The proofs need to be explained well enough that they can be communicated
并被数学共同体理解，对吗？
and understood by the mathematical community, okay?
它们不能只是人工产物，
They can't just be artifacts, you know,
不能只是某种令人印象深刻的成就，
just sort of impressive achievements
却不能在数学中带来任何后续进展。
that don't lead to anything further in mathematics.
它们需要被理解。
They need to be understood.
所以我们需要生成写得好的解答。
So we need to generate solutions that are well written.
目前，AI 虽然正在加速这个过程的前两个阶段，
Now currently, AIs, while they are accelerating the first two stages of this process,
但在这第三个阶段仍然相当薄弱。
they are still quite weak in this third stage.
它们擅长阐述的某些方面，但其他方面不行。好吗？
They are good at some parts of exposition, but not others. Okay?
例如在最基础层面，拼写、语法、格式，
So for example, at the base level, spelling, grammar, formatting,
它们做得完美，甚至完美到这样的程度，
they're perfect at this, almost too perfect to the point
以至于人们现在反而更喜欢读稍微不那么完美的文本。
where people prefer to read slightly imperfect text at this point.
但这不只是技术上的，比如说，
But it's not just about just technically being, you know,
拼写正确等等。
spelling correct and so forth.
通常它们的重点非常奇怪。
Often the emphasis is very strange. Um,
比如 AI 生成的数学读起来非常令人沮丧。
like AI-generated mathematics is very frustrating to read.
你在寻找，最重要的、
Um, you're, you're looking for, um, you know, what was the most important,
最困难的部分，证明中最有趣的部分是什么。
was the most difficult part, was the, the interesting part of, of a proof.
而你会发现 AI 花的时间一样多
And you will find that the AI spends just
在一些非常平凡的引理上，比如说，
as much time on some very trivial lemma that that is, you know,
用三页来证明显然的东西，然后，
three pages to prove something obvious and then, like, you know,
却只用三行来证明。
three lines to prove.
而论证中真正有趣的部分，
Like the really interesting part of the, the argument, um,
它们也常常不披露这些影响来自哪里。
also they often don't disclose, uh, where the influences came from.
它们——我的意思是，这非常间接。
You know, they're, um, I mean, it's very indirect.
通常，证明会经由一些……
Often they, they, they, the proofs come through some, some,
一些来自训练数据的权重。
some weights which come from some training data.
而且在某个环节，某个先前的结果会间接地影响
And at some point, some, some previous result indirectly sort of influenced the
结果，但这些 AI 生成的文本，它们
result, but they, they often, um, uh, these, these AI-generated texts, they,
往往完全不披露，完全没有说明
they often disclose no, um, um, no sense.
这些联系从何而来。
of where these, these connections came from.
所以这些结果常常让我觉得过于脱离文献。
So it, the results often, I feel a lot more disconnected from the literature than they should.
也许这种情况以后会改善。
Um, you know, so, um, and, and maybe this will get better.
如果你假设 AI 能力会继续提升，它们
So if you, if you assume that that AI capabilities get better, you, you know, they,
在阐述方面正慢慢变得好一点。这更难，因为……
they are slowly getting a little bit better at exposition. It's harder, uh, because, um.
证明的验证，是一个清晰的真假信号。
Verification of a proof, you know, this is clear signal it's true or false.
你可以……
And, and you can, you can send,
可以有一个好的评分函数，并对它进行优化。
you can have a good scoring function and you can optimize it.
而这正是 AI 工具擅长的。
And that's what AI tools are good at,
但证明写得好不好。
whether proof is well written or or not well written.
我们对此还没有真正好的评判标准，
We don't yet have really good rubrics for this,
但也许将来会有，证明也会变得更容易阅读。
but maybe we will and maybe proofs will get easier to read.
但这也不一定是好事。
But that's not necessarily a good thing either.
有时一个证明可能过于巧妙。
Sometimes a proof can be too slick.
也许你经历过这种情况。
Maybe you've experienced this.
如果你读过某个证明，它不知怎的
If you've read a proof that has somehow been
其中所有困难都被打磨得一干二净，
where all the difficulty has been sanded down to nothing,
于是这个证明看起来毫不费力，
and then it seems like the proof is effortless
然后你回家试着用纸笔重新推导，
and then you try to reconstruct it at home in pen and paper
却做不到，因为它不知怎的把困难藏起来了。
and you can't do it because it has somehow hid the difficulty.
实际上，证明中包含一点我所说的“自然摩擦”是很重要的。
It actually is important for proofs to contain a little bit of what I call natural friction.
当一个人试图证明某件事时，
So when a human tries to prove something,
有些步骤很容易，他会轻松完成，
there are some steps that are easy and the human will just sail through them
不会花太多时间。
and not spend too much time on them.
而有些步骤确实很难，
And then there are some steps that really are hard,
他会停下来，花一些时间，
and the human will pause and take some time
尝试仔细组织证明，尽量少做多余的工作。
and try to organize the proof carefully and try not to do too much work and, um.
读者能感觉到这一点，并且能领会，
And the reader can sense this and the reader can pick up on this and,
理解证明的困难部分在哪里。
and understand where the, the difficult part of the proof is.
AI 对容易的事情会快速冲过去，
Um, AI is, you know, easy things they'll blast through,
但困难的事情它也会同样快速冲过去。
but also difficult things that also blast through.
看起来完全一样。
And it just looks the same.
而矛盾的是，实际上，人类在……
Um, and paradoxically, actually, you know, humans when they, um,
他们不这样做，并且在阐述中犯的错误，
they don't do this and they make mistakes in exposition,
反而在某些方面会帮助读者。
can actually help the reader in some ways.
这很矛盾，但确实如此。
It's, it's paradoxical, but it's true.
我举一个我自己经历的例子。
Um, so I'll give you one example of my own experience.
这篇论文，这是我那本 Jean Bourgain（让·布尔甘） 1991 年的论文副本，
Um, so this paper, this is a, um, my copy of a paper of Jean Bourgain from 1991,
是我读研究生时读的。
which, um, I read as a grad student.
内容关于 Kakeya 猜想和限制性猜想。
It's about the Kakeya conjecture and the restriction conjecture.
实际上，Hong Wang（王虹） 的工作，
Actually, uh, Hong Wang's, uh, work, uh, that was in, uh, in, uh,
昨天报告的工作，很多实际上都基于这篇论文。
presented yesterday is based, a lot of it is based actually on this particular paper.
对你们中从没读过 Jean Bourgain（让·布尔甘） 论文的人来说，这
Um, and for those of you who have never read a paper by Jean Bourgain, uh, it is,
是一次非常有教育意义的经历。
it is a very, very educational experience.
我至今还保留着自己当时的笔记，
Um, so, um, I still have the notes of myself from,
是读研究生时努力啃这篇论文的笔记。
as a grad student trying to get through this paper.
他会直接说，比如：“显然我可以做到”，还有“这个，
Um, and he would just say, you know, clearly I can do this and, you know, this, this,
这个命题是本质的。”
this, this statement is, is essential.
“这本质上等于那。”而我则写满了各种非常沮丧的问号。
This is essentially equal to this. And I have all kinds of very frustrated, uh, question marks.
你们可能看不清，但我有一个，
And so what, you probably can't see it, but I have a, uh,
这里的批注是“我恨 Jean Bourgain（让·布尔甘）”。
annotation here is that I hate Jean Bourgain.
好吧。
Okay?
但我还是努力啃下来了。
Um, but I, I fought my way through this.
我非常幸运，有 Elias Stein（伊莱亚斯·斯坦） 解释其中一些内容，Tom Wolff（汤姆·沃尔夫） 也解释了，
Um, I was very fortunate to have Elias Stein explain some of this and Tom Wolf explain,
最终我理解了他所做的事情。
and I eventually understood what he was doing.
实际上，那一次，我终于理解了他的思维方式。
And actually, it was, it was, I finally got the way he thought.
以及为什么某些我原本没看出等价的东西
And, and why certain things that I didn't see were equivalent,
基本上是等价的。
were basically equivalent.
我学到了很多，以至于几年后
And I learned so much, um, you know, to the point where actually a few years later,
我更喜欢读 Jean Bourguignon 的论文，而不是其他人的。
I, I preferred reading Jean Bourguignon's papers over all the others
因为我理解他的思维方式，而且他总是直入主题。
because I understood how his mind worked and like he just got straight to the point.
而且读起来总是很愉快。
Um, and it was always a pleasure to.
但这确实是一个学习的过程。
Read it. But it was definitely a learning process.
我想，如果他的证明经过很多层 AI 改进，
Um, and I think if his proofs have been passed through many layers of AI improvement,
我可能就不会得到当时那样的教育。
I may not have gotten the education I did.
是的。所以，这不仅仅是写论文的问题。
Um, yeah. So, um, right. So it's, it's not just about writing papers.
更重要的是真正消化和理解这些结果。
Well, it's about really digesting and understanding the results.
Bill Thurston 有一句名言，大致就是这个意思。
Um, and there's a famous quote of Bill Thurston to this, to this effect.
所以尽管表面看来，
So, you know, despite appearances,
我们并不是在努力完成某种抽象的定义生产配额、
we are not trying to meet some abstract production quota of definitions,
定理和证明；有时候，当你提交简历之类的材料时，
theorems and proofs or sometimes, you know, when you submit CVs and things,
看起来我们好像在做这些。
it looks like that's what we're doing.
衡量我们成功的标准，在于我们所做的是否能让人们理解，
The measure of our success is whether what we do enables people to understand
并且更清晰地思考数学。现在，即使你——
and think more clearly about math. Now, even if you.
生成一个证明，而且它是对的，你把它讲解得很好，而且——
Generate a proof and you it's correct and you explain it really well and it, and,
而且它具备所有天然的摩擦力，而且——
and, and, and you, and it has all the natural friction and it's, it's, it,
任何读它的人都会真正从中受益。
anyone reading it will actually benefit from it.
这仍然不够。
That's still not enough.
因为，要真正影响数学的未来发展，
Like, in, in order to actually influence the future development of mathematics,
它需要被共同体接受和重视。
it needs to be accepted and valued by the community.
其他数学家需要真的愿意去读它，
Um, you know, and other mathematicians need to actually want to read it
消化它，并把它融入自己的工作；当然，这可能不会自动发生。
and digest it and put it into their own work and it may not, you know, and of course,
把它做得正确且易读当然有帮助。
making it correct and, and easy to read helps.
但那只是一个充分条件，而不是必要条件。
But that's only a sufficient condition. It's not necessary.
这就像做饭一样，你可以做出一桌很美的饭菜，
You know, it's like, it's like cooking, you know, you can cook a beautiful meal and,
闻起来很香，而且——
you know, it, it smells great and, and you, and,
所有食物都已被验证为安全可食。
and all the food has been verified safe to eat.
但你不能强迫别人，也不应强迫别人去吃。
And that's, you know, but you can't force people or you should not force people to eat it.
这是他们自己的选择。
And, you know, and it's, it's their choice.
所以你需要说服其他人，
So there is this, you know, you have to convince other people that this,
这个结果是值得做的。
this result is, is worth doing.
直到最近，这都不是问题，因为证明非常稀缺，
Now, this wasn't a problem until very recently because proofs were so scarce
以至于一旦某个结果被证明，人们自然就会——
that the moment some, some result got proven, then naturally people,
领域里所有人都会放下手头的事，
everyone else in the field will just drop everything,
去读那篇论文，而且他们有动力这样做。
read the paper and they'd be motivated to.
继续推进。
To you know.
基本上就像食物稀缺时，
So, you know, basically it's like if food is scarce,
桌上端来什么你就会吃什么。
you will eat whatever is delivered onto the table.
但现在我们被证明淹没，数量超过我们能够阅读的量，
But now we are flooded with proofs and more than, more than we can read,
我们现在必须挑挑拣拣。
and we now have to pick and choose.
因此，我们现在需要被说服才会真正去读证明。
Um, and so we, um, we need to be convinced to, uh, to actually read proofs now.
阅读证明现在是最宝贵的瓶颈之一，一种稀缺资源。
Um, proof reading is now one of the most precious bottlenecks, um, scarce resources,
在这个新时代，你可以帮助、引导人们去——
um, in this new era, um, now you can help, you can induce people to, uh, to,
去读你的工作。
to read your work.
讲好故事会有帮助。
Um, telling good stories helps.
有一个展示过程的叙事，描述你是如何得到——
Having a narrative showing the process, describing how you arrived at, at, at, at,
这个结果的，哪些方法行不通，以及你如何绕过这些困难。
at the result, what didn't work and how you, how you went around it.
人们喜欢故事。
People love stories.
过去我们不强调过程。
We have in the past not emphasized process.
我们只是让结果自己说话，
We've just let the outcomes speak for themselves,
这一直有效，直到我们找到了自动化——
which has worked until we figured out ways to automate, you know,
没有过程的结果的方法。
outcomes without process.
而目前的工具对自身过程非常不透明。
And the current tools, they are very, very opaque about their process.
有一些叫做 chain of thought（思维链）的东西。
There are things called chain of thought.
你可以在某种程度上往“引擎盖”下看一眼，但它并不——
You can kind of look under the hood a little bit, but it doesn't,
它并不是很有洞见。
it's not very insightful.
现在，也许其中一些问题可以通过良好实践来改变，但是……
Now, maybe some of this just can be changed with good practices, but, um, uh,
但目前，尤其是当这些……
But currently, especially if these,
如果这些证明来自专有模型或内部模型，而……
if these proofs come from proprietary models or internal models where, uh, uh,
公司往往会被
companies often are
激励去将某些事实作为企业机密来保守，那么……
incentivized to keep certain facts corporate secrets, then, um, yeah, uh,
我们看不到过程，而且我们
we do not see the process, and we
这确实让我们更不愿意真正投入时间去
and this really makes us a lot less willing to actually invest the time to,
了解这些东西，因为我们
to learn about these things because we
我们看不到完整的故事。
We don't see the story.
所以解决问题还有第四个阶段。
So there is a fourth stage to solving problems.
所以不仅仅是生成证明、验证证明和解释证明，
So not just generating proofs, verifying them, and explaining them,
它们还必须被接受。
they have to be accepted.
而在我们目前的体系中，我们的发表体系是这样的，
And in our system currently, the way we have the publication system,
所以它们必须，标准的方式是让一个
so they have to be, you know, the standard way to have a
结果被共同体接受，就是把它发表在有声望的期刊上
a result accepted by the community is having it published in a reputable journal
所以它们必须被数学共同体消化和接受。
so they have to be digested and accepted by the mathematical community.
我们有一个体系。
And we have a system.
为此建立了体系，我们有期刊，但是很慢。
Set up for this, we have journals, um, but it's slow.
正如我说过的，你可以促进它，你可以让你的
Um, as I said, you can encourage it, you know, you can make your
论文读起来更有吸引力。
your papers more appetizing to read.
但不能只靠 AI 来优化这一点，因为它
Um, but you cannot just try to optimize this by an AI because it
它涉及人的回应。
it involves human response.
好吧，除非你以某种方式把人类接入 AI，这是我非常不建议的。
Okay, unless you somehow wire the human into an AI, which I really do not recommend.
所以这是过程中慢得多的一个部分，也是其中一个方面。
Um, so this is a much slower part of the process, and it is one way.
AI 目前基本没有产生影响。
AI has basically not made an impact currently.
是的，仍然是人与人之间的交流才会
Um, yeah, it is still humans talking to humans that require that
促成某种接受。
that induce some acceptance.
目前我们这样做的方式是，我们有期刊，
Now, the way we do this right now is that we have journals,
当一篇论文经过验证后，
and when a paper has been verified, you know,
它已经足够好，可以提交给期刊，
it's been good enough to submit to a journal,
我们把它交给人类审稿人，他们自愿
we send it to a human referee, and they volunteer
付出时间，作为服务来审阅这些论文，
their time as a service, you know, to referee these papers,
不仅仅因为结果有趣，
not just because the result is interesting,
还因为他们想鼓励作者成为更好的数学家。
but they want to encourage the authors to become better mathematicians.
这是一种促进
It's a way of promoting, um,
新一代数学家的方式。
another generation of mathematicians.
这不是有声望的工作。大家通常
Um, it's not prestigious work, you know. I mean, the people, you know, we, uh,
我们刚刚为解决问题颁发了四枚奖章。
we just gave four medals for solving problems.
我们没有为审稿颁发四枚奖章。
We didn't give four medals for refereeing.
但这是我们职业中至关重要的一部分。
Um, but it is an essential part of our profession, and you know it.
它把数学家的个人成就转化为集体理解。
It's how we convert individual achievements of mathematicians into collective understanding.
我的意思是，审稿人只是代理，但
Um, I mean, the referees are proxies, but, you know,
我们互相阅读论文，这个领域就是这样进步的。
we read each other's papers, and this is how the field progresses.
但它很慢，而且我们正面临一场危机：
But it's slow, and we are now facing a crisis that there's
有太多 AI 生成的论文，以至于即使它们是正确的，
so many AI generated papers that even if they're correct,
也可能多到审稿人读不过来。
there may be too many for referees to read.
这是一个持续存在的问题。
Now, this is an ongoing problem.
我想会有其他专题小组讨论如何应对这个问题。
I think there will be other panels discussing what to do about this.
我认为期刊也必须开始采用 AI 工具作为过滤器，
I think journals will also have to start adopting AI tools as filters,
而且我们必须对风格指南更加精确，
and we'll have to be much more precise about style guides
以及对各种期刊的规则，以便在任何论文到达人类审稿人之前，
and rules for various journals so that before any paper reaches a human referee,
还有一层额外的评估。
there's some additional layer of evaluation.
这会有争议，但我认为是必要的。但没错，你会。
This will be controversial, but I think it will be necessary. But yeah, you would.
你绝对不应该把人类审稿人从等式中去掉。
You should definitely not take the human referee out of the equation.
我会这么说。
I would.
我不认为一本完全依靠 AI 审稿人的期刊会成功，
I don't think a journal that purely operates on AI referees will be successful,
尤其是因为这些工具很容易被钻空子。
especially since these tools can be gamed quite a bit.
而且，如果有一本期刊说，哦，
And, you know, if there's a journal that says, oh,
这篇论文已经被 100 位 AI 审稿人接受了，
this paper has been accepted by 100 AI referees,
那还不是数学共同体的认可。
That's not community acceptance.
这仍然不意味着我们愿意去读它。
That still doesn't mean that we want to read it.
那么这就是我们的最终目标吗？
Okay, so is that our final goal?
即便那也不是我们的最终状态，真的。
Well, even that is not our final state, really, you know,
所以即使一个结果已经被数学共同体接受并发表
so even when a result has been accepted by the community and is published
并且发表在知名期刊上，人们都承认它是正确的。
and is in a prestigious journal and people all accept it as correct.
它仍然不是最终状态。
It's still not the final state.
最终状态是像教材这样的东西，那些，
The final states are things like textbooks, you know, the, the,
我们在课堂上教授的材料。
the material we teach in classes.
这个概念的规范定义是什么？
What is the standard definition of this concept?
我们证明事物的正确顺序是什么？
What is the correct order in which we prove things?
你如何把发表在优秀论文中的零散结果组织成一个连贯的理论？
How do you organize individual results published in good papers into a coherent theory?
那是我们数学家最终的……而且那
Um, that is the state which we mathematicians ultimately, and that
那才是我们试图解决的所有这些问题的最终状态。
that is the end state of all these problems that we're trying to solve.
所以介绍我上台的 Alex 为这个过程起了个很好的名字。
So Alex, who introduced me, has a very nice name for this.
它叫规范化。
It's canonicalization.
所以除了消化证明并发表它之外，你还要让它变得规范。
So in addition to digesting a proof and publishing it, you want to make it canonical.
而这是所有阶段中最慢的。
And this is the slowest stage of all.
过去十年、二十年里有很多结果，
You know, there's many, many results in the last 10 years, 20 years that, you know,
它们发表在知名期刊上，但还没有进入教材。
they're in prestigious journals, but they're not in textbooks yet.
它们还没有被教授给学生。
They're not yet taught to students.
我们还没有找到真正确定、规范且正确的方式来
We haven't yet figured out the really definitive canonical correct way to
教授这些东西。
teach these things.
而且这很慢。
And this is slow.
我的意思是，你必须去教课，必须获得反馈，而且
I mean, you have to teach classes, you have to get feedback and,
你还必须非常认真地思考，什么才是正确的方式，去
and you have to really think hard about what is the correct way to, or to,
去组织大量的
um, to organize lots and lots of.
不同的结果，并把它们放进一个连贯的叙述中。
Of, um, different results and put them in one coherent narrative.
这需要共识，如果，
Um, and it needs consensus, you know, I mean, if it would be, you know,
如果一个领域里一半数学家认为你应该这样做，
if half the mathematicians in a field think you should do things this way
而另一半则认为应该用另一种方式。
and the other half a different way.
那我们就还没有规范化。
Then we don't have canonicalization.
而在这个阶段，AI 基本上完全无用。
Um, and this is the stage in which AI is basically completely useless.
所以可以说，几乎没有，不，我，我，
Um, so, um, like there's, there's sort of, no, I, I,
我基本上认为 AI 在过程的这一部分几乎没有任何作用，
I see basically almost no role for AI in this part of the process,
但它是最有价值的部分，
but it is the most valuable part um that
如果你想把数学的任何一个子领域应用到其他某个数学领域或
if you want to apply any subfield of mathematics to some other area of
数学或某个问题上。
mathematics or some problem.
它几乎必须被消化成这种形式，比如，如果，
It pretty much has to be digested in this form, you know, like if,
如果你想让一个数学领域对工程师或物理学家或
if you want a field of math to become useful to engineers or physicists or,
或者生物学家等等。
or biologists, whatever.
我的意思是，他们不会去翻，最新的论文，
I mean, they're not going to dig through, you know, the most recent papers in,
在《数学年刊》之类的期刊里翻找。他们想要的是教材。
in the Annals of Mathematics or whatever. They want the textbooks, um, and many, yeah.
所以数学最有价值的应用，
So the most valuable applications of,
只有在你达到这个最终阶段之后才会被解锁，
of math only get unlocked once you have reached this final stage,
包括 AI 本身。
including AI itself.
我的意思是，AI 在数学中如此成功的一个重要原因，
I mean, a big reason why AI is so successful in mathematics,
是因为几个世纪以来我们一直在建立这些规范定义。
it's because for centuries we've been building these canonical definitions.
我们有这些教材，关于线性代数如何运作，
We have these textbooks, um, of, you know, how does linear algebra work,
群论如何运作？
how does group theory work?
我们拥有所有这些非常，
You know, like we have all these very,
非常成熟的理论，而 AI 已经吸收了所有这些。
very mature theories and AI has absorbed all of these.
这就是它用来取得成功的东西。
Um, and that's what it uses, um, to, uh, for success.
所以如果我们长期切断这一部分过程，那将会，
Um, and so if we cut off this part of the process, long term, uh, it will,
这会损害数学。
it will hurt mathematics.
是的。所以，抱歉我说了这些。
Um, yeah. So, um, sorry I said all that.
所以也许这才是最终的，目标，所以，
So maybe this is the final, um, goal, so,
所以也许问题求解的真正目标不只是生成证明，
so maybe the real goal of problem solving is not just to generate proofs
不只是验证它们，不只是解释它们，也不只是发表它们。
and not just to verify them, not just to explain them and not just to publish them.
而是要真正地，把所有这些证明组织成一个规范的状态，使它们成为定论。
But to actually, um, organize all those proofs into a canonical state to make them definitive.
所以最后这三个阶段，我喜欢称之为“证明消化”。
So these last three stages, I like to call proof digestion, you know,
所以这不只是制造食物，而且
So it's not just sort of creating food, and
甚至不只是吃下它，你还必须消化这个证明
And not even just eating it, but you have to sort of digest the proof
并将其内化到它真正成为数学体系一部分的程度。
and internalize it to the point where it really becomes part of the body of mathematics.
现在，这个过程甚至可能继续延伸。
Okay, now, it is possible that this process even continues more.
但这些是我能够识别出的五个阶段。
But these are the five stages that I was able to identify.
但你可以看到，清楚地陈述目标这件事会让你走得很远，
But you can see that the exercise of stating your goals clearly can take you quite
远到偏离你原本以为的过程。
far from what you might think the process is.
而这个小小的解构揭示了一件事，
And this little deconstruction reveals one thing,
那就是，AI 正在做的是创造出大量的，好吧，
which is that what AI is doing is that it is creating lots and lots of, well, okay,
如果这是证明消化的过程，
if this was the process of proof digestion,
那 AI 现在产生的就是我所说的“证明消化不良”。
what AI is producing is what I call proof indigestion. Um,
如果你是一名电气工程师，
if you're an electrical engineer.
你可能会把它称为阻抗失配。
You might call it impedance mismatching.
因为 AI 在这个过程的前两个阶段比
Um, because AI is much better at the first two stages of this process than it
后三个阶段要擅长得多。
is at the last three.
我们正在，开始看到各种各样的消化不良。
Um, we are, you know, beginning to see all kinds of indigestion.
我们看到证明不断累积，却尚未被验证。
We're seeing proofs accumulate that haven't been verified.
我们看到已验证的证明，却没人会去读。
We're seeing verified proofs that no one will read.
我们看到可读的证明，却没人会发表。
We are seeing proofs that are readable, but no one will publish.
而这还没有发生。
And this isn't happening yet.
但如果我们外推，很快还会出现一大堆已发表的、由 AI
But if we extrapolate, we will soon also get a big pile up of published proofs AI
生成的证明，没人知道如何将它们转化为像样的教材
generated that no one knows how to convert into, like, proper textbooks
并教育下一代。
and educate the next generation.
所以这些都是富足带来的问题。
So these are all problems of abundance, you know.
所以粗略地说，世界上的所有问题都可以分为
So, roughly speaking, all the problems in the world can be classified into
稀缺的问题和富足的问题。
problems of scarcity and problems of abundance.
好吗？比如食物，有饥荒和营养不良。
Okay? So for food, for example, you know, you have famine and malnutrition.
这些是食物稀缺的问题，
These are problems of food scarcity,
但你也会面临肥胖、缺乏锻炼，以及，不良饮食。
but you also have obesity and lack of exercise and, um, bad diet.
而这些是食物富足的问题。
And these, these are problems of food abundance.
因此我们几个世纪以来一直生活在证明稀缺的时代。
Um, and so we've lived for centuries in the era of proof scarcity.
但如果我们相信这个工作假说，我们将非常，
Uh, but we are going to, if we believe this working hypothesis, we will very,
很快进入证明富足的时代。
very soon be in an era of proof abundance.
我们必须适应。
Uh, and we have to adapt.
就食物而言，我们的适应方式是更清楚地意识到什么
Um, and in the case of food, we adapted by becoming much more conscious about what
是好的饮食，什么不是。
is good eating and what is not.
什么是好的锻炼，什么不是。
What is good exercise, what is not.
我们的品味提高了，我们的饮食水平也提高了。
Our taste improved. Our cuisines improved.
我们拒绝了一些食物，它们在技术上可食用，
We rejected some food that, you know, is technically edible,
但我们不会吃掉盘子里的所有东西。
but we don't eat everything that's on our plate.
我认为在数学中我们也必须做类似的事情。
Um, and we have to do something similar in mathematics, I think.
所以一旦你更清楚自己的目标是什么，
Um, so once you have a clearer idea of what your goals are,
你就真的可以开始制定政策。
then you can actually start making policies.
然后你就可以真正开始处理这个共同体回应的问题。
Then you can start actually attacking this community response question.
所以我想，这件事的一个起点，你们许多人已经听说过。
So I think a first start of this, many of you have heard about this.
所以去年在莱顿开始了一项草根行动。
So there was a grassroots effort starting in Leiden back last year.
许多数学家在一个AI 与数学研讨会上意识到了这一点
Many mathematicians in a workshop on AI and mathematics realized this
并开始尝试制定一份共识声明，
and started trying to make a consensus statement,
吸引了许多共同体成员，包括在座的很多人，
drawing in many members of the community, including many people here,
来起草现在所称的《Leiden Declaration》（莱顿宣言）。
to draft what's now known as the Leiden Declaration.
这并不能解决这些、这些问题，
And this is, this doesn't solve these, these problems,
但它是我们需要继续做更多的那类事情。
but this is the type of thing we need to do, continue to do more of.
所以这份声明陈述并阐明了当前局面：AI 在做什么，
So, this declaration states, lays out the situation, what AI is doing,
数学在做什么，数学的意义是什么。
what math is doing, what math is about.
至少是在共同体很大一部分成员能够
Uh, at least to the extent that, uh, a large fraction of the community can,
认同的范围内。
can agree with it.
而且这份声明有很多签署者。我自己也签署了
And there are many, many signatories of this. I've signed this,
这份声明。
this declaration myself.
并且其中有一些实际建议
Um, and there are practical recommendations
一旦你理解了这些目标，
that become clear once you understand the goals and, uh,
以及你们共同体的价值观，这一点才会变得清晰。
and values of your community.
所以我真的建议，如果你还没看过，去认真读一读这份宣言。
So I really would recommend, if you haven't seen it, to actually read this declaration.
它，经历了多次迭代，
It is, um, it has been, it's, it's been going through many iterations, um,
很多人提供了反馈，目前它已经是一份相当不错的文件。
and many people supplied feedback and it's quite a good document at this point.
它包含很多建议。比如，
Um, and it has many, many, um, recommendations. Um, so one, for example,
对个人来说，其中一条是始终披露 AI 工具的使用。
for individuals is to always disclose AI tool use.
也许将来这一点会变得没有必要，
Um, maybe in the future this will become unnecessary, you know,
比如，我们现在已经不再声明使用 LaTeX 了。
we don't disclose LaTeX use anymore, for instance.
但在我们当前这个时代，我认为这真的非常重要。
Um, but in our current era, it is, it's really important, I think. Um.
我特别认为，有一种情景
Particularly, I think the one scenario
在当前时代我们真正想避免的，是那种人们——
that we really want to avoid in this current era is where people are,
每个人都在偷偷使用 AI，却没有人披露，
everyone is secretly using AI and no one is disclosing it
也没有人分享自己的最佳实践和错误。
and no one is sharing their best practices and their mistakes.
这对弄清如何正确使用 AI 会非常有害。
And this is going to be really harmful for working out how to use AI properly.
所以我们确实需要让负责任地披露 AI 系统成为常态。
So we really need to normalize responsible disclosure of AI systems.
所以本着这种精神，我确实用 AI 生成了这些文字，不是为了写破折号，
So in that vein, I have used AI to generate these texts, not for the em dashes,
但有几个地方自动补全很有用，而且这些图表
but there's a couple of places where autocomplete was useful and the diagrams
比如你们看到的这些图表就是 AI 生成的。
that you saw were AI generated, for instance.
好的，但其他文本是我自己写的。
Okay, but the other text was written by myself.
我们需要让审稿人的工作轻松很多。
We need to make life a lot easier for referees.
我们不能只是用 AI 生成一大堆上百页的证明，
We cannot just generate lots and lots of hundred-page proofs by AI,
然后直接甩给审稿人。
just dump them on referees.
我们需要让这件事容易得多。
Um, we need to make it much easier.
我们，负担会转移到作者身上，也就是，
We, the burden will shift onto authors to, to, it'll be,
作者将有责任让自己的论文达到——
it'll be incumbent on authors to, to make their, their papers at,
达到最高的阐述标准，
at the highest expository standard, um,
披露所有工具，并根据需要使用形式化方法。
disclosing all their tools using formalization as needed.
总的来说，我们需要从流程的第一阶段走出来，对吗？
Um, and we need to, in general, just move away from the first stage of the process, okay?
过去，我们强调真正重要的是成为第一个
So in the past, we would emphasize what was really important was being the first to
证明定理的人，也就是证明的生成。
prove a theorem proof generation.
这曾经是——这是主要任务，其他一切都只是收尾。
This was the—this is the main task and everything else was cleanup.
现在我们自动化了这第一步，它不再是瓶颈。
Now we've automated that first step and that's no longer the bottleneck.
因此，一个已经生成但没有整理、还不能发表的证明，
So a proof that has been generated but not cleaned up and made publishable.
也就是说，我们应该只把它视为不完整的证明，
That is, we should, we should value that only as an incomplete proof, uh,
还没有准备好发表。
not yet ready for publication.
我们确实需要开始重视证明的消化。所以最后三个阶段，
And we really need to start valuing proof digestion. So the three final stages,
阐述、发表和规范化。
exposition, publication and can, and canonicalization.
我们，现在确实重视这些，但我们应该更明确地，
We, um, we do value these right now, but we should be much more explicit about, um,
要提升它们的重要性。
about, um, about, um, raising their importance.
我们需要恰当地进行贡献归属。
Um, and we need to, uh, attribute things properly.
有一个争论：如果你按一下按钮就得到证明，
You know, there's a debate, you know, if you pushed a button and you got a proof,
你有资格成为那篇论文的作者吗？
do you get to be an author of the paper that came out?
所以 Leiden Declaration 对此有所说明。
So the Leiden Declaration has something to say about this.
我的建议是，如果一位作者不能像在这里一样就这个结果做报告，
My suggestion is that if an author cannot give a talk like up here about the result
也无法就他们生成的结果回答问题，
and they cannot take questions about the result that they generated,
他们就不应署名，或者至少论文还没有准备好发表，
they should not be an author or at least the paper is not ready to be published
除非至少有——
unless there is at least.
一个能真正把结果讲清楚的人。
One person who can actually talk about the result properly.
对。
Yeah.
所以我解构了其中一个，
So I've deconstructed one, you know,
我画了一张关于数学所有目标的图，
so I had this diagram of all the goals of mathematics,
它向各个方向分支开来。
and it branched out all over the place.
其中有一个方向，就是解决问题。
And I had one direction, which was solving problems.
我的观点是，它远比那种天真的图景复杂得多，
And my point was that it is far more complicated than sort of the naive picture of
那种图景只是试图解决尽可能多的问题。
just trying to solve as many problems as possible.
好的，但你可以解构它。
Okay, but you can deconstruct it.
你就能理解我们是什么——这正是我们实际在做的事——并且
You can understand what we are—that's what it is we're actually doing—and
这确实能澄清那个方面。
that really clarifies that aspect.
好的，这会影响期刊应如何运作，以及
Okay, so you know, and this informs like how a journal should operate and
以及我们应该如何评估问题求解能力，以用于未来招聘等等。
and how we should assess problem solving for future hiring and so forth.
但我们关心的许多其他目标，也还有许多其他方面，
But there's many other parts of many other goals that we care about,
而这一工作假设最终也会影响到所有这些方面。
and this working hypothesis will eventually impact all of them as well.
所以我们也需要做，就像我刚才对问题求解所做的那样，
So we need to also do, so what I just did for problem solving,
人们也需要对教学、指导、招聘、基金申请这些方面做同样的事，
people also need to do for teaching, for mentoring, hiring, grant applications,
公众传播，以及我们职业的每一个方面，都应该摆到桌面上讨论。
outreach, every single aspect of our profession should be on the table and discussed.
而我们需要对它们全部加以分析。这是一场很长的讨论。
And we, we need to analyze them all. And that's a big lengthy discussion.
而我只有 10 分钟，所以这些我都不准备展开讲。
And I only have 10 minutes. I'm not going to talk about any of those.
是的。所以，回应会有所不同，
Um, yeah. So, um, and the response will be different in, in, in,
对于我们职业的不同部分。
for different parts of our profession.
我认为，我们职业中的某些部分
I think there will be some parts of our profession
基本上必须限制 AI，尤其是在教育和培训方面，
where we basically have to restrict AI education and training in particular,
我认为，这可能是有害的，
I think it is, uh, it can be harmful to, to,
让学生过早使用太多 AI。
to give students too much AI use early on.
他们确实需要先发展自己的，
They do need to develop their own, um,
内在的数学能力，然后才能学习使用这些工具。
innate mathematical skills before they can learn to, uh, uh, to use these tools,
就像我们教人们算术，
you know, just like we, we, we teach people arithmetic
在他们使用计算器之前；或者，我们教人们先……
before they do calculators or we, we teach people to.
学会走路和跑步，然后才把车钥匙交给他们。
To walk and run before we give them the keys to a car.
数学也是这样。
Uh, same in math.
还有其他一些地方，我们应该使用 AI，
Um, there are other places where we should, um, use AI,
但我们应该主动行动，并且决定，
but we should take the initiative and, and decide what are, uh,
我们对哪些类型的 AI 使用是可接受的，设定自己的规则。
what we set the rules on, on what types of AI use are acceptable.
哪些类型不可接受；也不要让外部力量为我们定义规则。
Which ones are not and not let external actors define the rules for us.
还会有一些地方，像期刊这样的传统渠道就是不适合
There will be some places where traditional venues like journals are just not
这种现代 AI 工作流。我们确实需要创建新的工作流，
suitable for this modern AI workflow. We do need to create new workflows,
新的基础设施。
new infrastructures.
这又是另一个小时的演讲，很遗憾我在这里没有时间展开。
That's another hour talk, which I unfortunately do not have time to give here.
但最重要的是，我们确实需要公开讨论所有这些问题，并且
But most importantly, we really need to discuss all of these questions openly and,
不要只是被动地，成为发展的接收者。
and, and, and not just be passive, you know, recipients of, of developments.
但我们需要讨论 AI 的能力，需要讨论我们的目标和价值观。
But we, we need to discuss AI capability, we need to discuss our goals and values.
我们还需要讨论数学共同体的回应。
And we need to discuss community response.
这也是 Leiden Declaration 的一项主要建议。
And this also is a major recommendation of the Leiden Declaration.
我就讲到这里。非常感谢。
So this is where I will stop. Thank you very much.